Francisco Nunes

Born: December 20, 1987—Porto, Portugal Nationality: Portuguese & Brazilian

Email: francisco.nunes@fraunhofer.pt Personal page: http://francisconunes.me

Scholar: https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=D2rDc98AAAAJ

Twitter: @xico_nunes

Research interests

I am interested in learning about people and how they use technology. My projects are usually at the intersection of computer science, medicine, design, and social sciences. I am an expert in ethnographically informed design, user-centred design, and participatory design approaches.

Broad keywords for my work would be: Human-Computer Interaction, Computer-Supported Cooperative Work, Health Informatics, and Science and Technology Studies.

Education

2012-2017 PHD in Informatics (Human-Computer Interaction), TU Wien

Thesis: "The Everyday Life with Parkinson's and Self-care Technologies". Supervised by

Geraldine Fitzpatrick.

2005-2010 MSc & BSc in Informatics and Computing Engineering, University of Porto

Thesis: "Healthcare TV Based User Interfaces for Older Adults". Supervised by Teresa Galvão

and Paula Alexandra Silva.

Experience

2017-now	Senior researcher, Fraunhofer Portugal AICOS, Porto
2016-2017	Researcher, NOVA-LINCS, Universidade Nova de Lisboa, Lisboa
2012-2017	PhD Student, Institute for Design and Assessment of Technology, TU Wien, Vienna
2010-2012	Researcher, Fraunhofer Portugal AICOS, Porto
2008-2010	Research Assistant, Fraunhofer Portugal AICOS, Porto

Grants, honours & awards

Acquired project grants

"Smartphones for Smart Seniors (S₄S)" funded by ANI (Portugal) − €137K Lead proposal writer. "Personal Health Device for the Remote and Autonomous Management of Parkinson's Disease (REMPARK)" funded by FP7-ICT (EU) − €411k

Co-proposal writer.

"CellPipe UI" funded by Alcatel-Lucent – €49k

Co-proposal writer.

2011

OTHER GRANTS AND HONOURS

2016	Two special recognitions for an 'Excellent Review' at CHI 2016
2016	Grant for attending conference from TU Wien (€1390)
2015	Grant for attending CHI 2015 doctoral consortium (\$1300)
2012	Vienna PhD School of Informatics scholarship (3 years of funding)
2012	Dance! Don't Fall was on the Top-25 Apps, CES Mobile Apps Showdown
2011	Smart Companion was 2nd most creative app, ZON Creativity Award (prize: €6250)
2010	Mover was 5th best Lifestyle app, Android Developer Challenge II (prize: equipment)

Teaching & supervision experience

Courses

Summer 2015 HCI in Healthcare (MSc) – Co-teaching and supervision of student projects at TU Wien Winter 2014 User Research Methods (MSc) – Co-teaching and supervision of student proj. at TU Wien

Supervised students

ongoing	Cristiana Braga (MSc), Evaluation of a system for shiftworkers working in healthcare
ongoing	João Almeida (MSc), Restaurant recommendation system for people with food allergies
2015	Martin Herndl (BSc), Developing an Android Self-Management Application for People
	with Parkinson's Disease
2012	João Cevada (MSc), User Interface Design Recommendations for Fitting Smartphone Ap-

plications to Persons With Parkinson's

Projects

Ongoing

2016-2019

2015-2018

²⁰¹⁴⁻²⁰¹⁸ Clockwork (EU AAL-JP) – This project is developing technologies to support the self-care of shift workers. Since April 2017, I am the PI at AICOS, in charge of supervising the user research, design, and evaluation of the smartphone app and the smart badge. I also coordinate the project consortium. http://clockworkproject.eu/

Physio@Home (PT 2020) – This project is developing a solution for physical rehabilitation, at home and at clinic, using wearable sensors and serious games. Since June 2017, I am the PI at AICOS, in charge of supervising the design and evaluation of the serious games. MASPARK (La Marató de TV3) – This project is developing a system that can detect and address freezing of gait in patients with Parkinson's. Since April 2017, I am the PI at AICOS, in charge of supervising the design and evaluation of the system.

SELECTION OF PREVIOUS PROJECTS

²⁰¹¹⁻²⁰¹⁵ REMPARK (EU ICT-FP7) – This project developed a wearable system to monitor symptoms of people with Parkinson's, intervene in the gait, and collect data to improve the therapy. I participated in the first year of the project and was involved in user research and early design phases of the smartphone apps for patients. http://www.rempark.eu/

Smart Companion (Internal) – This project created an Android skin specifically designed for older people. I participated in the user research, design, and evaluation of the smart-phone applications. Smart Companion is today being sold by GOCIETY under the name GOLIVEPHONE. http://smartcompanion.projects.fraunhofer.pt

eCAALYX (EU AAL-JP) – This project created a telehealth system for older adults with chronic conditions. I participated in the the user research, design, and evaluation of the TV interfaces for older adults. http://ecaalyx.org

Mover (Internal) – This project created an Android app that explored the accelerometer to capture activity and thus promote movement. I participated in the design and evaluation of the app. Mover is today being sold as part of the GOLIVEPHONE mentioned above. http://mover.projects.fraunhofer.pt/

Service

PROGRAM COMMITTEE MEMBER

Mindcare 2016

2016

2014

PervasiveHealth 2016
PervasiveHealth 2015

And in workshops at CHI'16, GROUP '14, Ubicomp '13, and SouthCHI '13

Workshop organizer

Designing Self-care for Everyday Life at NordiCHI '14 (link)

Designing Systems for Health and Entertainment: what are we missing? at ACE '14 (link)

Reviewer

ENTCOM, Health Informatics Journal, IJCCI, IJHCS, IxD&A, JAMIA, JCSCW, JMIR, TOCHI. CHI ('18, '17, '16, '15, '14), CSCW ('17, '16, '15), DIS '18, Group '16, Healthcom '13, MobileHCI '17, NordiCHI ('16, '14), PervasiveHealth ('17, '16, '15).

STUDENT VOLUNTEER

CHI ('16, '13), CSCW '15 PC meeting, NordiCHI '10

Publications & talks

H-index: 9; citations: 237 (source Google Scholar as at 01/2018)

Proceedings and special issues edited

- P. A. Silva, F. Nunes, eds. (2016) "Special issue on fun and engaging computing technologies for health", *Entertainment Computing*, 15: 41–70
- N. Verdezoto, F. Nunes, E. Grönvall, G. Fitzpatrick, C. Storni, and M. Kyng, eds. (2015) "Proceedings of Designing Self-care for Everyday Life. Workshop in conjunction with NordiCHI 2014, 27th October 2014, Helsinki, Finland", *DAIMI Report Series*, 41(597).
- N. Verdezoto, F. Nunes, G. Fitzpatrick, and E. Grönvall, eds. (2014) "Designing Self-Care For Everyday Life", *Interaction Design and Architecture(s) Journal IxD&A*, 23: 142–190.

JOURNAL ARTICLES

- F. Nunes, T. Andersen, and G. Fitzpatrick (2017) "The agency of patients and carers in medical care and self-care technologies for interacting with doctors", *Health Informatics Journal*, 1–20.
- F. Güldenpfennig, F. Nunes, and G. Fitzpatrick (2016) "Making Space to Engage: An Openended Exploration of Technology Design with Older Adults", *International Journal of Mobile Human Computer Interaction*, 8(2): 1–19.
- F. Nunes, P. A. Silva, J. Cevada, A. C. Barros, L. Teixeira (2015) "User Interface Design Guidelines for Smartphone Applications for People With Parkinson's Disease", *Universal Access in the Information Society*, 15(4): 659–679.
- F. Nunes, N. Verdezoto, G. Fitzpatrick, M. Kyng, E. Grönvall, and C. Storni (2015) "Self-care Technologies in HCI: Trends, Tensions, and Opportunities", *ACM Transactions on Computer Human Interaction*, 22(6), article 33: 1–45.
- F. Nunes, and G. Fitzpatrick (2015) "Self-care Technologies and Collaboration", *International Journal of Human Computer Interaction*, 31(12): 869–881.
- A. Aguiar, F. Nunes, M. Silva, P. A. Silva, and D. Elias (2012) "Leveraging electronic ticketing to provide personalised navigation in a public transport network", *Intelligent Transportation Systems Transactions and Magazine*, 13(1): 213–220.

CONFERENCE PAPERS (PEER-REVIEWED)

- F. Nunes, and G. Fitzpatrick (2018) "Understanding the mundane nature of self-care: Ethnographic accounts of people living with Parkinson's", *Proc. of CHI 2018*
- A. Vasconcelos, F. Nunes, A. Carvalho, C. Correia (2018) "Mobile, Exercise-agnostic, Sensor-based Serious Games for Physical Rehabilitation at Home", *Proc. of TEI 2018*
- F. Güldenpfennig, Ö.Subasi, F. Nunes, M. Urbanek (2017) "UbiKit: Learning to Prototype for Tangible and Ubiquitous Computing", 31st British HCI Conference
- F. Güldenpfennig, F. Nunes, and G. Fitzpatrick (2015) "Proxycare: Integrating informal care into formal settings", in *Proc. of PervasiveHealth* 2015, 141–144.
- P. Jordan, P. A. Silva, F. Nunes, and R. Oliveira (2013) "mobileWAY A System to Reduce

- the Feeling of Temporary Lonesomeness of Persons with Dementia and to Foster Intercaregiver Collaboration", in *Proc. of HICSS 2013*, 2474–2483.
- P. A. Silva, F. Nunes, A. Vasconcelos, M. Kerwin, R. Moutinho, and P. Teixeira (2013) "Using the Smartphone Accelerometer to Monitor Fall Risk While Playing a Game: The Design and Usability Evaluation of Dance! Don't Fall", in *Proc. of HCII 2013*, 754–763.
- F. Nunes, M. Kerwin, and P. A. Silva (2012) "Design Recommendations for TV User Interfaces for Older Adults: Findings From the eCAALYX Project", in *Proc. of ASSETS 2012*, 41–48.
- M. Kerwin, F. Nunes, and P. A. Silva (2012) "Dance Don't Fall Preventing Falls and Promoting Exercise at Home", in *Proc. of pHealth 2012*, 254–259.
- A. Vasconcelos, P. A. Silva, J. Caseiro, F. Nunes, and L. F. Teixeira (2012) "Designing Tablet-based Games for Seniors: the Example of Cogniplay, a Cognitive Gaming Platform", in *Proc. of Fun & Games 2012*, 1–10.
- P. A. Silva, and F. Nunes (2010) "3 x 7 Usability Testing Guidelines for Older Adults", in *Proc. MEXIHC* 2010, 2: 1–8.
- F. Nunes, P. A. Silva, and F. Abrantes (2010) "Human-Computer Interaction and the Older Adult: an Example Using User Research and Personas", in *Proc. of PETRA 2010*, 49: 1–8.

POSTERS AND EXTENDED ABSTRACTS (PEER-REVIEWED)

- T. Marques, F. Nunes, P. A. Silva, and R. Rodrigues (2011) "Tangible Interaction on Tabletops for Elderly People", in *Proc. ICEC 2011*, pp. 440--443.
- T. Sousa, P. Tenreiro, P. A. Silva, F. Nunes, and E. Rodrigues (2011) "Cross-platform social web application for older adults with html 5", in *Proc. ICEC 2011*, pp. 375--378.

Position papers (juried)

- P. A. Silva, F. Nunes (2016) "Preface for the special issue on fun and engaging computing technologies for health", in *Entertainment Computing*, 15: 41–42.
- F. Nunes (2016) "The medication reminder as enforcing a medicalised perspective on daily life", in *Book of abstracts of the 6th STS Italia Conference*, 58.
- F. Nunes (2015) "Designing Self-care Technologies for Everyday Life: A Practice Approach", in *Proc. of CHI EA 2015*, 215–218.
- N. Verdezoto, F. Nunes, G. Fitzpatrick, E. Grönvall (2014) "Preface to the Focus Section", in *Interaction Design and Architecture(s) Journal IxD&A*, 23.
- F. Nunes (2013) "Improving the Self-care of Parkinson's Through Ubiquitous Computing", in *Proc. of Ubicomp Adjunct 2013*.
- F. Nunes and, P. A. Silva (2011) "The Smartphone A Mobile Companion for Older Adults", in *Proc. of Promoting and Supporting Healthy Living by Design Workshop at INTERACT 2011*, 41–43.
- P. M. Teixeira, P. A. Silva, F. Nunes, and L. F. Teixeira (2011) "Mover Activity Monitor and Fall Detector for Android", in *Proc. of Mobile Wellness Workshop at MobileHCI 2011*.
- F. Nunes, and P. A. Silva (2010) "Fostering Wellness of Older Adults While Performing Usability Testing", in *Proc. of HCI4WELL Workshop at HCI2010*.
- A. Aguiar, F. Nunes, M. Silva, and D. Elias (2009) "Personal Navigator for a Public Transport System Using RFID Ticketing", in *Proc. of inMotionog Workshop at Pervasive 2009*.

INVITED PRESENTATIONS

12/09/2017	"Self-care technologies" at the course Qualitative methods and co-design of self-care tech-
	nologies of University of Copenhagen, Denmark.
6/09/2016	"Self-care technologies" at the course Qualitative methods and co-design of self-care tech-
	nologies of University of Copenhagen, Denmark.
14/09/2015	"Understanding and Promoting the Creation of Patient Knowledge Online" at University
	of Trento & FBK, Italy.
17/08/2015	"How can technology help people improve their self-care? Supporting engagement in
	their clinical consultations" at IT University of Copenhagen, Denmark.
17/08/2015	"Designing Self-care Technology for People with Parkinson's: A Focus on Everyday Life"
	at University of Copenhagen, Denmark.
27/10/2014	"The Self-care of Parkinson's" at the Designing Self-care for Everyday Life Workshop at
	NordiCHI 2014 in Helsinki, Finland.
12/07/2012	"Design recommendations for TV user interfaces for older adults" at the Interactive As-
	sistive Technologies for the Elderly Workshop in University of Aveiro, Portugal.
06/05/2011	"eCAALYX project" at the course Multimodal Interfaces of University of Porto, Portugal.

MEDIA MENTIONS

Mover was mentioned in the Jornal de Negócios (30/04/2010) and Diário de Notícias (29/05/2010). Smart Companion was described in RTP (01/08/2011), Porto Canal, and another time at Porto Canal (26/07/2012) when I was even interviewed.

Languages

Portuguese – native English – proficient Spanish – fluent French – intermediate (DELF A4 certificate) German – intermediate (B1.1 certificate)

References

Geraldine Fitzpatrick, TU Wien (geraldine.fitzpatrick@tuwien.ac.at)
Paula Alexandra Silva, University of Aveiro (palexa@gmail.com)
Nuno Correia, Universidade NOVA de Lisboa (nmc@fct.unl.pt)

Last updated: March 12, 2018